Since we have such little information,
情报实在太少了
we should prepare just in case it doesn't have a mind.
最好以它没有心智的状况来做准备
In that case, we'll have to use sheer force.
这样一来就只能用蛮力硬攻了
Is that possible?
行得通吗？
I don't know.
不知道耶
Um, in that case…
那个 如果是这样的话…
I might be able to kill Mistress Frieren.
我说不定能杀掉芙莉莲大人
Yeah?
是吗？
Yes.
是的
Well then, let's draft up a plan.
这样的话 来制定作战计划吧
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田钟人 作画：阿部司）
First, let's make sure we're on the same page.
那首先先确定彼此的理解一致
In the event that the clone has a mind,
假设复制体具有心智的话
we'll use Edel's hypnosis magic
那就用艾蒂露的精神操作魔法
to break through my mental defense.
击破我的精神防御
-And to have Fern kill me. Is that right? -Yes.
-然后让菲伦杀了我 没错吧？ -是的
How can you say "yes" so easily?
不是吧 怎么答得这么轻松？
Dünste.
托斯特先生
Where is Edel?
艾蒂露小姐呢？
We were attacked by Sense's clone,
我们受到赞泽的复制体攻击
and she dropped out of the exam.
她不得不放弃考试
I see. And Blei as well?
原来如此 布莱先生也是吗？
I was able to run to safety because he bought me time.
多亏有他帮我争取时间 我才得以逃脱
I hope he was able to escape safely.
希望他也能顺利脱身就好了
Don't mind me! Go!
别管我！快走！
But…
可是…
Anything's better than having zero participants pass.
不管怎样 总比没人合格好吧
I have information.
我有情报
Will you cooperate with me?
你们要跟我合作吗？
I was willing to do that from the very beginning.
老夫从一开始就打算这么做
Is there anyone who can heal?
现场有人有治愈能力吗？
I have Scriptures, so I can perform simple healing magic.
我有《圣典》 可以施展简单的回复魔法
Thank you.
有劳了
I see.
这样啊
So the clones don't have minds.
所以复制体并不具有心智
That's right. According to Edel,
是的 依艾蒂露之见
they're just imitating the workings of a mind very precisely.
它们只是单纯 很精确地模仿了心智活动
But they don't have a real mind.
但是并不具有真正的心灵
Now there is no easy way of defeating it.
所以没有能够轻松打败它的手段呢
We have to draft up a plan with that in mind.
那么就要以这点为前提 拟定作战计划了
That being said,
话虽如此 芙莉莲
there are still too many unknown factors.
还有许多不确定因素
The biggest issue to focus on
最大的问题在于
is the identity of those clones and the caster of the spell.
复制体的身分以及施术者的本体
We can't take action until we understand their nature.
还没了解它们的性质前 不能轻易采取行动
We especially need to find out if they really don't have any weaknesses.
而且复制体真的没有任何弱点吗？
If that clone is really on the same level as Frieren,
万一复制体真的跟芙莉莲的实力相当
some of us may end up dead.
可能就会有人伤亡
I won't give any answers.
我不作回答喔
I thought so.
我想也是
It doesn't have any weaknesses.
它确实没有任何弱点
The one manipulating the clones
操控复制体的施术者
is a monster from mythical times called Spiegel.
是神话时代的魔物 水镜恶魔
Lawine.
拉比涅
How do you know?
你怎么会知道？
My oldest brother was part of the advance party sent by
我哥哥刚好是大陆魔法协会之前
the Continental Magic Association to raid the Ruins of the King's Tomb.
派遣前去攻略零落王墓的先锋队队员
So you had information?
所以你早就有情报了？
No wonder you were able to make it this far.
怪不得你能抵达这里呢
But what you did wasn't very logical.
但你的所作所为并不合乎情理
If you knew, you should have
如果你早有情报
shared this information and cooperated with us from the beginning.
打从一开始你就应该 分享情报给我们 跟我们合作
No one seemed to be in the mood to cooperate.
当时的氛围并不像是能够进行合作
Plus, Frieren and Fern went in ahead of us before we knew it.
而且芙莉莲她们 早在我们察觉到前就走掉了
And you, old man,
而且大叔你啊
are the type to abandon your comrades if it's not against the rules.
是那种只要没有硬性规定 就会抛弃伙伴的类型吧
Why would we cooperate with you?
怎么可能会跟你合作呢？
You really got on their bad side.
你真的被讨厌了呢
I am, indeed, an old man.
我确实是个大叔
But it hurts when you say it to my face.
但是当面被这么叫还是很伤人
-You should probably apologize. -Sorry about that, old man.
-你还是道个歉比较妥当吧 -真是抱歉喔 大叔
According to the observations of the advance party,
根据先锋队的观察
Spiegel is on the other side of that door,
水镜恶魔就在那扇门后面
inside the treasure vault.
宝库的内部
Supposedly, the monster itself
据说魔物本体很弱
is weak and has no means of attack.
并且不具有攻击手段
If you defeat it, all the clones will disappear.
只要打败它 所有的复制体都会消失
That matches up with the results from our mana detection.
这点与我们 使用魔力感知后的结果一致
The monster is beyond that door.
魔物本体就在那扇门的后面
But that door has a powerful binding spell cast on it.
但是那扇门 遭到强力的封印魔法封住了
I noticed that too.
我也确认过了
My clone must have done that.
是我的复制体干的好事
The spell that shuts the door of a treasure vault at the risk of your life.
奋力将宝物库的大门封住的魔法
It's one of the most powerful binding spells in all folk magic.
是民间魔法中最强大的封印魔法
That door will not open unless the caster dies.
除非施术者死亡 不然那扇门永远打不开
We could ignore the door completely and break down the wall,
虽然也可以完全无视那道门 直接破坏墙壁
but it probably has a workaround for that too.
但它很可能也已经作了应对措施
Either way, in order to get to Spiegel,
不管怎样 想要接触到水镜恶魔
we have no choice but to defeat that clone.
就只有打倒那个复制体这个办法了
Then you'd better hurry up.
要的话 最好动作要快点
What do you mean?
你这是什么意思？
Spiegel creates clones of everyone inside the dungeon.
水镜恶魔会创造 身处迷宫所有人的复制体
And those clones
而那些复制体
instinctively flock to the innermost depths over time.
随着时间过去 会本能地往迷宫最深处聚集
Aside from my brother's unit,
之前的先锋队中
most of the members of the previous advance party were annihilated.
除了我哥哥所在的部队 其他小队大多遭到歼灭了
They were annihilated right here,
就在最深处的房间前
just before the innermost depths.
这处大厅里
I see.
原来如此
Excuse me.
不好意思
The clones imitate the workings of a mind very precisely, right?
复制体只是单纯很精确地 模仿了心智活动 对吧？
That means they have the same behavioral weaknesses
也就是说 它们在行为模式上
as their originals, right?
具有与本体相同的弱点 是吗？
Most likely.
恐怕是这样没错
In that case, we might have a chance.
真的是这样的话 我们还有击败它的机会
What is this "weakness" you're talking about?
那你说的弱点是什么？
Mistress Frieren,
芙莉莲大人
can you please stand by that wall over there?
可以请您站到那边的墙边吗？
Sure.
好
This is…
这是…
It can't be…
不会吧…
Unbelievable…
怎么会这样…
Did you notice?
你们注意到了？
-Do you get it? -No.
-你看出端倪了吗？ -没有
This is, indeed, Frieren's fatal flaw.
这确实是芙莉莲致命的弱点呢
Why didn't I notice this when I fought her?
跟她战斗的时候 我怎么没发现这点呢？
No…
不…
I knew she was skilled, and that preconception prevented me from noticing.
我早就知道她实力坚强 是预设立场让我无法注意到这件事
The moment she uses magic,
在她发动魔法的那一刻
her mana detection is interrupted for a split second.
她的魔力感知会短暂中断一下
Isn't that a common mistake made by apprentice mages?
那不是见习魔法才会犯的错误吗？
I've always been bad at that.
我打从以前就不擅长这件事啊
If you were aware of it, why didn't you tell us?
您既然知道的话 为什么不告诉我们呢？
Because it's embarrassing.
因为很难为情嘛
Now is not the time to be saying that.
现在是说这种话的时候吗？
But all her other skills are just too exceptional.
但是她在其他方面的能力太优秀了
Very few mages would be able to actually
鲜少有魔法使能够
take advantage of her flaw.
抓住这项破绽反击吧
Anyway, let's just start a strategy meeting.
总之 我们开始作战会议吧
Even if we get rid of Frieren's clone…
就算能除掉芙莉莲的复制体…
Mistress Frieren, you look like you're having fun.
芙莉莲大人 您看起来很开心呢
Yeah.
是啊
Sounds like we have a plan.
看来大致有个底了吧
Eisen, you distract the monster while I attack from the side.
艾泽 我从旁进攻时 你去引开魔物的注意力
Frieren, you provide covering fire.
芙莉莲就负责掩护攻击吧
What about Heiter?
那海塔呢？
He has a hangover, so he's useless today.
他还在宿醉 今天派不上用场
He's dead.
昏死过去了
I just remembered how
我只是想起了
we used to have discussions like this when we fought dungeon bosses.
以前在打迷宫首领时 也曾经有过这样的会议
All right.
好了
Let's start our raid.
开始攻略吧
Can we win?
吾等赢得了吗？
Don't worry.
放心吧
There is no such thing as a dungeon that can't be raided.
世上并不存在攻克不了的迷宫
I'm the mage from the party
我可是史上攻克过
that has raided the most dungeons in history.
最多迷宫的小队中的魔法使喔
Are you sure you want to fight Frieren's clone
跟芙莉莲的复制体作战
all by yourselves?
真的靠你们两个就够了吗？
It's easier to predict your opponent's movements when there are fewer people.
人数越少越能够预测敌人的动向啊
Yes.
没错
It's true that we would most likely win if we all fought together,
如果全员一起战斗 确实胜算比较大
but most of us would die in the process.
但大多数人可能就会战死
You probably won't even have time to use your evacuation golem.
应该连使用魔像 逃生的时间都没有喔
So you're saying
而且话说回来
it is more important
拦住那些
to stop the clones that will come to the innermost depth?
往最深处聚拢的复制体更重要
After all, we'd all be wiped out if we got attacked from both sides.
毕竟要是遭到夹击的话 可能就会全军覆没的
Okay, let's go according to plan.
那么就依计划行事
All right. I wish you good luck.
好吧 祝你们好运
Go ahead and open it.
好 开门吧
Well then…
那现在…
Let's go around and say who the toughest opponent would be for each of us.
我们轮流说说 自己最应付不来的对手吧
Judradjim.
破灭之雷魔法
It's moving exactly how Mistress Frieren predicted.
跟芙莉莲大人预料的行动一样
Vollzanbel.
地狱业火魔法
Its mana detection was interrupted.
它的魔力感知中断了
My clone will be wary of Fern, who hid during that time.
复制体在警戒刚刚趁机躲起来的菲伦
But it will be too busy fighting me, its evenly matched opponent.
但它光是对付势均力敌的我 就已经忙不过来了
It won't have time to search for Fern.
根本没时间去找菲伦的所在
After all,
说到底
nobody knows how dangerous I can be more than I do.
没人比我自己更清楚我能有多可怕
Don't worry.
不要紧的
When you perfectly conceal yourself,
把自己藏得无懈可击的菲伦
even I can't find you that easily.
连我都无法轻易找到喔
But are you sure that Zoltraak is the spell I should
但是真的只需要用杀人魔法
use to attack?
攻击就好了吗？
It's the quickest spell to fire.
因为这招攻击速度最快啊
Plus, Zoltraak is
而且杀人魔法
a relatively newer spell among elves.
对精灵而言是比较新的魔法
It hasn't been around long enough
所以我们还没有
for our reflexes to automatically defend us.
习惯成自然的自动反射防御
In order to counter it, we have to think,
无论如何都需要一点时间
so it takes a little longer,
才能反应过来
even if it's just a split second.
尽管那不过只是一瞬间而已
But not for you, Fern.
但你就不一样了
For you, Zoltraak is something
杀人魔法对你来说
that has always existed from the time you were born.
是自打你出生以来就存在的东西
It's fundamental magic that comes naturally to you.
已经是你牢记在骨子里的基础魔法
Your Zoltraak would be able to kill me.
菲伦的杀人魔法是足以除掉我的
Put in all the mana you have.
将你所有的魔力都注入进去吧
Frieren,
芙莉莲
you don't like me, right?
你其实不喜欢我吧？
Why did you come see me?
为什么还要来见我呢？
To tell you the truth, I thought I'd never see you again.
老实说 我以为应该不会再见到你了
I came to deliver my master's will.
我是来送师父的遗书的
It's been 50 years…
自那之后已经过了五十年了啊
I see. So Flamme died, huh?
这样啊 所以说伏拉梅死了吗？
You're not sad?
你不难过吗？
I only raised her on a whim.
我会抚养她也只是一时兴起罢了
It's basically a report.
简直就是份报告书嘛
What did she write?
里面写了什么？
Apparently, the emperor authorized the research
她说皇帝已经同意全国
of magic on a national level.
进行魔法的研究
Up until now, magic was viewed
至今为止 因为人类
as the art of demons among human societies,
视魔法为魔族的技术
so studying it indiscreetly was considered taboo.
因此公开研究也被视为禁忌
Flamme was the one who proposed the idea,
提出这个点子的人就是伏拉梅
and she took part in teaching the newly established Imperial Mages.
她还参与了新设宫廷魔法使的教学
She basically wrote to me
她希望我
to ask me to take over in her place.
替她接下教学的工作
How greedy is she?
那家伙有多贪心啊？
Just getting the authorization for researching magic was a feat.
单单是让皇帝同意魔法研究 就已经是个壮举了
But she wants more?
她竟然还想要更多吗？
Is this such a big deal?
那是很了不起的事情吗？
This means the largest empire on the continent will begin researching
这表示大陆上最大的国家会开始
and applying magic for military use.
研究魔法 并用于军事用途
The nations around it won't be able to ignore that.
周遭的国家自然不会坐以待毙
In just a few decades,
只需数十年的时间
magic will become widespread throughout the continent.
魔法就会传遍整个大陆
A day will come when all of mankind will be able to use magic.
无论是谁 都能使用魔法的时代就要来了
In the not too distant future,
在距今不久的将来
mankind will gain the power to fight against the Demon King's army.
人类就会得到 足以与魔王军抗衡的力量
I see. That's pretty incredible.
这样啊 那真的很了不起呢
I know.
真是的
But
但是…
that is not what I want.
这可不是我所希望的呢
Go home, Frieren.
回去吧 芙莉莲
There is no way I am going to agree to this will.
我不可能听从这份遗言
It's extremely annoying.
真是令人不爽
"A time where anyone can use magic," you say?
“谁都能使用魔法的时代”？
Magic should be special.
魔法应该是特别的存在
I don't plan to teach anyone without talent.
我没打算把魔法教给没有才能的人
To think she would send me this…
居然给我这种东西…
Flamme and I could never agree until the very end.
伏拉梅跟我直到最后 也无法认同彼此呢
She's just an apprentice I raised on a whim, after all.
毕竟不过是 我一时兴起培养的弟子而已
Master said,
师父说过
"Serie will most likely get mad and rip up the will."
“赛丽艾很可能会气到把遗书撕掉”
But she still wanted to tell you anyway,
就算如此 她还是想要告诉你
that her dream came true.
她的梦想成真了
Don't ask me why.
真是搞不懂呢
Well, I'll be off now.
那么我就走了
I don't think we'll ever meet again.
我想以后我们不会再见面了
Frieren.
芙莉莲
Before that, want to take a little walk?
你走之前要不要去散个步？
We have all the time in the world, anyway.
反正我们拥有最多的就是时间
It was Flamme's dream to see the day when anyone
任何人都能使用魔法的时代
could use magic.
是伏拉梅的梦想
At first, it had nothing to do with wanting to save mankind
最初其实跟拯救人类
or fight the Demon King's army.
或与魔王军抗衡没有半点关联
She didn't care about any of that.
她根本不在乎那种事
Do you know her favorite spell?
你知道她最喜欢的魔法是什么吗？
The spell to create a field of flowers.
是变出花田的魔法
It's a stupid spell that has no use whatsoever.
是无聊透顶、一点用处都没有的魔法
She really loved magic.
那孩子真的很爱魔法
She sincerely wished for everyone in the world to be able to
她是真心希望世上所有人
cast spells like that.
都可以施展魔法
It gave me the creeps.
真是令人不悦
It sounded like a little girl's cutesy dream.
听起来就像小女孩的可爱梦想
But that's exactly what it was.
然而 事实也确实是如此啊
It was a pipe dream that she shared with me when she was
这是那孩子的个子比我
a little girl who was much shorter than me.
还矮小很多的时候就有的梦想
Honestly, I thought
坦白说 我认为
that day wouldn't come for a while
还要很久才会迎来那样的时代
and that she couldn't possibly make it come true.
那孩子不可能实现梦想
But in her short lifetime,
可是就在她短短的生命里
which amounts to almost nothing in my eyes,
在我眼中几乎等同于无的生命里
she was able to become the progenitor of mankind's magic.
她成为了人类魔法的开创始祖
Master was always quick to make decisions.
师父她向来很果断
It was as if she was pressed for time.
就好像被什么追着跑一样
Humans have a limited lifespan.
人类的寿命有限
They are closer to death than we are.
他们比我们更接近死亡
There are many times
在人生里
in life when you have to make big decisions,
一定会遇上需要做出重大决定的时刻
and humans like her cannot afford to postpone making them.
作为人类是无法之后再做决定的
For us, we could do it 100 or 200 years later.
我们的话 就是一百年或两百年后再决定都可以
Even if we put it off for 1,000 years, it wouldn't make any difference.
延到千年后再决定也不会有差别
The time we have is close to an eternity.
因为我们拥有接近永恒的时间
Frieren,
芙莉莲
a long time has passed since humans first created
自从人类创造出所谓的文明后
what we call civilization.
已经过了很久
From here, the generations will come and go rapidly.
以后世世代代的发展会更迅速
In a mere millennium…
只需要一千年
In a mere millennium, it will become the era of humans.
再一千年 属于人类的时代就会到来
Humans will overtake us.
人类会超越精灵
Don't neglect your training, Frieren.
不要疏于修行了 芙莉莲
If anyone can kill you,
能够取你性命的人
it will be the Demon King
若不是魔王
or a human mage.
就是人类的魔法使喔
How exciting, Serie.
真令人期待呢 赛丽艾
That means I will get to see lots of mages
接下来 我会见识到更多魔法使
and all kinds of spells.
还有各式各样的魔法了
Well then.
那么
-Let's get it over with. -Both might die.
-赶紧结束这一切吧 -两个人都可能会死
-Wow. -I'll leave it to you.
-真是厉害 -交给你了
-This won't work either. -Mistress Frieren.
-这次也不行 -芙莉莲大人
-I expected it. -I have no choice but to do it.
-如我所料 -果然只能这么做了
So this is the height of magic?
《魔法的高深境界》
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译：洪贞韵